<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hidden manna or, the mystery of saving grace. Wherein the peculiarity of Gods especiall grace to the elect is asserted and proved, and divers objections of Pelagians and Arminians about the power of the will of man to supernatural good, are fully answered and confuted. By that reverend, learned, and faithfull minister of Gods word, William Fenner B.D. late of Rochford in Essex. Perfected many years since by the author whilst he was preacher at VVillingsworth in Staffordshire. Imprimatur Edm. Calamy.</title>
            <author>Fenner, William, 1600-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1310_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209026</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867935</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867935</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85207)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 175:E1310[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hidden manna or, the mystery of saving grace. Wherein the peculiarity of Gods especiall grace to the elect is asserted and proved, and divers objections of Pelagians and Arminians about the power of the will of man to supernatural good, are fully answered and confuted. By that reverend, learned, and faithfull minister of Gods word, William Fenner B.D. late of Rochford in Essex. Perfected many years since by the author whilst he was preacher at VVillingsworth in Staffordshire. Imprimatur Edm. Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Fenner, William, 1600-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R.I. for S. Bowtell, at the Bible in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Pelagianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hidden Manna: OR, <hi>The Myſtery of Saving Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein The peculiarity of Gods eſpeciall Grace to the Elect is aſſerted and proved, and divers Objections of <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> about the power of the Will of man to ſupernaturall good, are fully anſwered and confuted.</p>
            <p>By that Reverend, Learned, and faithfull Miniſter of Gods Word, <hi>William Fenner</hi> B. D. late of <hi>Rochford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perfected many years ſince by the Author whilſt he was Preacher at <hi>VVillingſworth</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Joh. 14. 22.</bibl>
            <q>Judas <hi>ſaith unto him (not</hi> Iſcariot) <hi>Lord, how is it that thou wilt manifeſt thy ſelfe unto us, and not unto the world?</hi>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>S. Bowtell,</hi> at the Bible in Popeſ-head Alley. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE Worſhipfull my very loving Friends, Mr. <hi>John Wollaſton</hi> (now Sir <hi>John Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſton</hi> Kt. and Alderman of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Thomas Parkes</hi> Eſquire. Grace and peace from our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He will of man is more wilfull, then the underſtanding blinde; The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſpeaking of the Learned Scribes and Doctors, ſaith, <hi>They have known the way of the Lord, but they have
<pb facs="tcp:169752:3"/> altogether broken the yoke,</hi> Jerem. 5. 5. more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then blinde; yea, the very Pagans, <hi>When they knew God, they glorified him, not as God,</hi> Rom. 1. 21. Yea, <hi>They were haters of God,</hi> ver. 30. <hi>who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Judgements of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chryſ.</note> 
               <hi>God, that they which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch things are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of death, not only doe the ſame, but have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them, and doe them,</hi> ver. 32. The reaſon why I ſay a wicked man ſinnes more out of wilfulneſſe, then blindneſſe is, three fold; the firſt is taken <hi>à causâ,</hi> from the cauſe, becauſe his wilfulneſſe is the cauſe of his blindneſſe: <hi>For fooles hate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169752:3"/> Prov. 1. 22. <hi>or at leaſt they regard not to know it,</hi> Prov. 29. 7. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this only true of thoſe people that have preaching, who actually refuſe inſtruction, and will not learne amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, of whom the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks; <hi>They know not, neither will they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,</hi> Pſal. 82. 5. But it is true alſo of thoſe blinde ſoules, that live under blinde Guides, they doe potentially, and <hi>innato habitu,</hi> reject the Doctrin of newneſſe of life, of whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes; <hi>Speake not in the eares of a foole, for he will deſpiſe the wiſdome of thy words,</hi> Prov. 23. 9. The ſecond is taken <hi>ab effectis,</hi> from the
<pb facs="tcp:169752:4"/> effects, becauſe the effect ſhews his wilfulneſſe, more then his blindneſſe; He knowes that drunkenneſſe, and company-keeping is a ſinne, yet he will live in it; he knowes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terloquutory ſwearing is a ſinne, and yet he will continue in it; That worldlineſſe, or<note place="margin">Video me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora ſequor.</note> pleaſure-hunting is a ſinne, yet he will goe on in it; like <hi>Ovids</hi> Medea, that knew the good, and yet would not doe it; his ſinne is not ſo much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the ſinne, as hatred of good: <hi>The wicked ſhall be caſt away for his malice,</hi> Prov. 14. 32. and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> calls the ſinne of the wicked, <hi>A roote of Gall and Worm wood,</hi> Deut. 29. 18. they are ſharpe and
<pb facs="tcp:169752:4"/> piquant againſt purity, and bitter againſt the power of godlineſſe; they are ſaid to walke after the ſtubbornneſſe of their heart, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. all ſhewing, that they are more wilfull, then blinde. What wilt<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thou ſay now, ſaith S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome?</hi> thou knoweſt not what things are to be done? thou both knoweſt them, and willingly refuſeſt to walke in them. The third is taken, <hi>ab experientiâ,</hi> from experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, experience tells us, that the wicked are more wilfull, then blind! wherefore elſe could <hi>Elias,</hi> that was a Prophet thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares, and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> that was a Prophet in his roome ſixty yeares, wherefore could they doe no more good upon
<pb facs="tcp:169752:5"/> the people? Wherefore does St.<note place="margin">Hierom. <hi>&amp;</hi> Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorus.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> after his ſo many ſcores of yeares teaching, breake off with this ſpeech? <hi>He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill,</hi> Revel. 22. 11. The Drunkard heares us preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt drunkenneſſe, and he will not obey; the Blaſphemer heares us preach againſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and he will not be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; the Church-ſleeper hath heard his Church-ſleeping condemned, and yet he will not mend it. If <hi>Nero</hi> could not endure <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſlept at his Muſicke, how can God endure ſuch as ſleepe at his Word? yet no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration.</p>
            <p>Whence we ſee, that the will is more corrupt by wilfulneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:169752:5"/> then the underſtanding by blindneſſe; <hi>The heart is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull above all things,</hi> Jerem. 17. 9. <hi>Above all things;</hi> That is, the heart is corrupt above all things, namely, the will above all things elſe, and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the underſtanding. <hi>The heart of the wicked is like an Oven, as hot as fire,</hi> Hoſ. 7. 6. That is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the will is like a red hot Oven, where all ſins are baked with the heat of Concupiſcenſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wicked men are very oft ſaid to walke after the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs of their heart, <hi>Jer. 9. 14. Jer. 11. 8. Jer. 13. 10. Jer. 18. 12. Jer. 23. 17. Eccleſ. 11. 9.</hi> There be three reaſons why the Will is
<pb facs="tcp:169752:6"/> more corrupt of the twaine:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ratione Originis,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Will was it that firſt rebelled againſt God, for the Serpent could not have decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the underſtanding of <hi>Eve,</hi> unleſſe ſhe would; the underſtanding as long as it was in innocency could not be deluded by the Devils guile, unleſse it would, for otherwiſe God had made the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding imperfect with a ſinfull ignorance; the underſtanding it ſelfe like a naturall Agent, underſtands, and works, <hi>ad ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum virium,</hi> as well as it can, and it ſuſpends not its conſideration it ſelfe; now it is the Will only that is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially free, and a free worker of its owne workes; and now
<pb facs="tcp:169752:6"/> freely itching to ſinne by its privie influence into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſuſpends it, not to conſider, and <hi>libertate participatâ,</hi> by a participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted freedome, not to obſerve Satans policy. Thus <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> willingly guld, ate the forbidden fruit, and firſt ſinning willingly, they and we are moſt puniſhed in the wil, moſt corrupted in wil. And therefore all ſinne is devolved upon the heart, as the firſt inward cauſe thereof. The Atheiſm of the Atheiſt is caſt upon the heart; <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God,</hi> Pſal. 14. 1. The miſchiefe of the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous is turned upon the heart, <hi>But miſchiefe is in their
<pb facs="tcp:169752:7"/> hearts,</hi> Pſal. 28. 3. the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the vaine man is truly fathered upon the heart; <hi>His heart gathereth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to it ſelfe,</hi> Pſal. 41. 6. Our Saviour Chriſt ſets all corruption upon the hearts ſcore; <hi>Out of the heart proceede evill thoughts, Murthers, Adulteries, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, Thefts, Falſe Witneſſes, Blaſphemies,</hi> Matth. 15. 19. St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c</note> addes more; Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, touchy, teaſty words, filthy talking, &amp;c. And I may adde, Out of the heart proceeds drunkenneſſe, and company keeping, &amp;c. That is, out of the wil, for the heart is commonly put for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ratione reatus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:169752:7"/> the will is it that indeed is guilty of all the evill in the ſoule, yea of all the ſaid errors, and ignorance of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And therefore ſaith God of the wicked, <hi>They doe alwayes erre in their heart,</hi> Pſal. 95. 10. Errour is not in the heart, but in the minde, and underſtanding; but ſayes the Text, <hi>They doe erre in their heart,</hi> becauſe they doe erre, and they would erre. <hi>They walked in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and imaginations of their evill heart,</hi> Jerem. 7. 24. Counſels and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations are properly in the underſtanding and minde, and not in the heart; but ſayes the Text <hi>They walke in the counſels and imaginations
<pb facs="tcp:169752:8"/> of their evill heart.</hi> For the underſtanding, as it ſayes the ſinne is delightfull, and gainfull to fleſh and bloud; ſo it would ſay alſo, that it is forbidden by God, and puniſhed with death; but the will gives eare to that word, the pleaſingneſs and the profit of ſinne, but will hear no more, or elſe bridles the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that it conſider, no further. And therfore theſe broken counſels, the imaginations by halves, as interrupted ones of the heart, are of the heart. Hereupon it comes to paſſe, that as the will is free by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive diſpoſition, and the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding free by participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo is the underſtanding blinde, and ignorant, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb facs="tcp:169752:8"/> ſubjectively by innate errour, and the will by a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular communication. And ſeeing the will is guilty of all the evill in the ſoule, all the blame God layes upon the will, and plagues it with the ſoreſt ſpiritual plagues, that it is moſt wilful.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ratione ipſius,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of it ſelfe, becauſe the will was beſt while it was<note place="margin">Corruptid optimi peſsima.</note> good, now it becomes worſt when it is bad. As a good King is the beſt of men, ſo a wicked Tyrant is the worſt of men. A good heart is Gods; <hi>My ſon give mee thy heart, Pr. 23. 26.</hi> A wicked heart is the devils; <hi>Satan hath fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy heart, Act. 5. 3.</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conceit of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:169752:9"/> is not evill; <hi>But every imagination and thought of the heart is onely evill continually, Gen. 6. 5.</hi> The heart is the fountaine, <hi>Jam. 3.</hi> And when God would curſe all the rivers &amp; ſtreams, he curs'd the fountaine, the heart. Now as in a corrupt fountaine, the nearer ye come to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine head, the more corrupt the water is, ſo the nearer the heart, the more corrupt. And therefore the outward actions being corrupt, the outward members are more corrupt; they being corrupt, the fancy is worſe corrupt; that corrupt, the underſtanding is worſe corrupt; that being corrupt, the affections are ſtill worſe and worſe corrupt; and they
<pb facs="tcp:169752:9"/> being corrupt, the heart is worſt of all corrupt; for that<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ.</note> is the fountaine. Out of the abundance of the heart the minde thinketh, the ſenſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth, the fancie imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the mouth ſpeaketh, the hand worketh, the foot walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, out of the abundance of the heart; ſo that that which is at all in the other faculties and members of the man, is in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance in the heart.</p>
            <p>Whence againe we ſee that the will does not alwayes follow the underſtanding; for the Wiſe-man preſuppoſeth that a mans underſtanding may be right, and yet the will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it; and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Be ye wiſe, and refuſe it not,</hi> Prov. 8. 33. Thus how
<pb facs="tcp:169752:10"/> many thouſands, their owne knowledge, yea and their owne conſcience haling them from, yet will runne upon ſinne: The envious, revengeful, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious man, his owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge teſtifies againſt this ſin, and yet he will revenge; his owne conſcience reproves him for this ſinne, and yet hee will beare malice. The lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the civiliſt, his own knowledge in the Scripture tels him, he muſt live holier and ferventlier, his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience checks him for not living better, and yet hee will not live better; Like the knowing Phariſees, <hi>Ye are of your father the devill, and the luſts of your father yee Will doe,</hi> Joh. 8. 44.
<pb facs="tcp:169752:10"/> Indeed its true, that the will muſt needs follow one dictate or other in the underſtanding, for it cannot ſee its object but by the underſtandings ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles. Nevertheleſſe the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding having nothing but a political or a ſuaſive power over the will, it can but tender the diſ-junction, and leave the aſſumption to the wils choice, for any imperative power that it hath. As for example, worldlineſſe; true, it is a gainful ſinne, you may be better to live to the eye of the world, that you may get by it: but then it is a dangerous—ſayes the underſtanding. Let me have it, let me have it, ſayes the will; I will cark, I will care for the world &amp;c. This I
<pb facs="tcp:169752:11"/> will doe, I <hi>will</hi> pull downe my barnes, and I <hi>will</hi> build greater, and there will I beſtow all my fruits, and my goods, <hi>Luke 12. 18.</hi> and then I <hi>will</hi> ſay to my ſoul, &amp;c. <hi>v. 19.</hi> I grant likewiſe, that an inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate act of the will preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth an errour in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding too; I ſay, an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the underſtanding, but not alwayes an erring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; it preſuppoſeth <hi>errorem materialem, non ſemper formalem,</hi> in caſe the will immediately before this inordinate act were an incorrupt will, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding an inlightened underſtanding, as the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> before their fall. It is a goodly Apple,
<pb facs="tcp:169752:11"/> faire to ſee to, ſweetly likely to taſte on, and the Serpent tels me I ſhall not dye, ſayes the underſtanding: Well, I will put it to the hazard, I will eat it, ſayes the Will. Theſe were the ſeeds of an errour, but not an errour it ſelf, till by the wils intervening itch, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding began to be darkned in a moment. Now that the will, will not follow the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alwayes, may appear by theſe reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the bleſſed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, albeit extrinſecally they be confirmed in grace, and by the vertue of extrinſecal actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, are finally, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, and intrinſecally ſetled in their wils upon grace, yet they have an inbred radical
<pb facs="tcp:169752:12"/> mutability of will poſsibly to depart from the grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe, if the will muſt needs follow the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then there could bee no ſinne in the wil againſt knowledge, much leſſe the diſtinct and illuminate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which is to be ſeene in the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, wherein the wilfulneſſe of the wil, lifts up the heele a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very face of more ſpecial knowledge. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there bee ignorance, yea the myſticalleſt and devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheſt ignorance of all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances admixt with that knowledge, yet that ignorance is not the cauſe, but a conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant of the wilfulneſſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:169752:12"/> 
               <hi>quatenus,</hi> as it is a ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Becauſe the will is ſo far from following the Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the more under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the underſtanding is in goodneſſe, the ſtouter the Will is; as is evident by the wicked, who the more they grow learned, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorly, the further they are from the maſtery of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt wils. Some of the deepeſt heads, that could anſwer all the objections in their braines by their extracted Science out of the Word of God, that any carnal man can bring to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to live in any one ſinne, and declare that they muſt live ſo and ſo, if they themſelves meane to be ſaved;
<pb facs="tcp:169752:13"/> yea and in this particular, at this particular time, together with all the circumſtances of preſſe knowledge, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding have unſanctified hearts; and therefore <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> having charged us to be wiſe in underſtanding, hee chargeth us alſo to be wiſe in heart, <hi>Prov. 8. 5.</hi> yea, the good Saints of God, the more knowledge they have, the more their wils grow reſty from zeale, or from the ſtrength of zeale that they had before, notwithſtanding that grace hath abated the violence of their reluctant wils, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it a mortiferous blow. I know that Learning and knowledge puffeth up, and caſts a miſt before the eyes of
<pb facs="tcp:169752:13"/> the underſtanding, yet this doth not hinder the truth of the poſition, That the heart is more wilfull, then the minde is blinde; be it that the minde is blinded, yet the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe growing upon the knowledges ſtature, ſheweth plainly, that it is the more wilfull of the two, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Saving Grace being not ſo adverſe to the fleſh as the practiſe thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Salomon</hi> having bidden us get knowledge, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to love it with our heart; <hi>Get underſtanding,</hi> Prov. 4. 5. <hi>And love her, and ſhe ſhall preſerve thee,</hi> verſ. 6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe the argument of them which hold the will
<pb facs="tcp:169752:14"/> muſt needs follow the laſt dictate of the underſtanding, may be retorted upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; They ſay, it muſt and does, becauſe the Sinner never ſinnes a ſinne, which his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding knowes is a ſin, and that a perilous ſinne to his owne ſoule, and at this time too; but the Will goes further, and tells him, That it is a delightfull profitable ſinne, and there is hope that God will not be ſo ſtrict with him, as to damne him for it; O, Chriſt dyed for our ſinnes, and God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and at what time ſoever a ſinner doth repent him, &amp;c. and therefore I may doe the ſinne; I ſay, this may be recoyled back upon them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:169752:14"/> this is but a begg'd di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, which the wil would faine have, and therefore to gratifie its Luſts, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding like a partial Judge, and a fee'd Counſellour, and a crafty Lawyer, or elſe Jury, pleads, judges, and counſels, and gives Verdict according as the importunate Wil would have it.</p>
            <p>For the Underſtanding and Will, are ſomewhiles like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> brethren in evil, ſworne brethren in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. The Will will yeeld to the Underſtanding in ſome things, and the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Will in other things, for they are two wicked brats of a wicked parent ſoule. Other whiles the Underſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:169752:15"/> and the will are like two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing hounds in a collar, that neither the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will doe as the Will would, for ſometimes its made to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand a thing againſt the will, or ere the Wil be aware of it, nor the Wil doe, as the Underſtanding preſcribes it. Sometimes the Wil deales with the Underſtanding, as <hi>Nahaſh</hi> would with the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadites, plucke out its right eye, or draw it ſome other way, or ſhut it ſelfe that it may not looke upon this or that luſt, with Scripture looks, or Bible-glaſſes, but view it onely with the left eye, with reſpect to what gaine it wil bring in, what pleaſure it will afford, what credit it wil
<pb facs="tcp:169752:15"/> yeeld, what conformity it hath to ſelfe love.</p>
            <p>Thus the ſinner wil minde the ſinne, wil conceive the ſinne, wil invent reaſons to maintaine the ſinne, why? he would faine commit the ſinne: Thus the Will gives the Underſtanding its quue, and prompts it, what it would have ſaid, and then follows the advice when it hath done. Lewd things are in his heart, hee imagineth evil at all times, <hi>Prov. 6. 14.</hi> He imagineth, how ſo? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe lewd things were before in his heart. So that now we may ſee the deſperate eſtate of the corrupt will: It is not onely <hi>ſtupens voluntas,</hi> a Wil in a ſwoon, but dead; ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:169752:16"/> all the light to a dead man, whats he the wiſer? neither is it enough that the Will have a <hi>poſſe,</hi> a power of willing grace vouchſafed it, for the Will is more wilful, then impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. It is wel obſerved by S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> The Apoſtle doth not ſay, it is God that worketh in you the <hi>poſſe,</hi> but the Will: It is not ſaid, God worketh in you the power to wil, <hi>But it is God that worketh in you the will and the deed, Phil. 2. 3.</hi> It is not ſaid, <hi>I will put my Spirit into you, and cauſe you to bee able to walke in my Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> but <hi>Ego faciam ut faciatis,</hi> ſaith the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>I will make you to do it, Ezek. 36. 27.</hi> The will of
<pb facs="tcp:169752:16"/> it ſelfe, the more reaſon it hath to be turned, the more it is wilful, it hinches and winches, and ſnuffes againſt it: <hi>For ſinne taking occaſion by the</hi> [knowne] <hi>comande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment workes all manner of concupiſcence,</hi> Rom. 7. 8. <hi>Nitimur in vetitum ſemper, cupimuſque negata.</hi> Like the running torrent, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing to ſtay it, runs the ſlowlyer, <hi>at ab obice ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior,</hi> but being hindred, runs the fiercelier.</p>
            <p>Behold then here, what a ſecret the grace is, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts this profligat will, which I here preſent you with, and ſo much the rather you, <hi>Loving Sirs,</hi> becauſe I would have you have a <hi>depoſitum</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169752:17"/> of our Countries thankfulneſſe unto you, &amp; ſuch as you are in that famous City, that have like ſo many <hi>Joſeſes,</hi> brought your money and laid it downe at the Apoſtles feet, to the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Goſpel in our ignorant coaſts. The bleſſedeſt project that ever could come into any Chriſtian heart; for as the people might goe to Gods houſe, when the word of the Lord came from Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>Eſa. 2. 3.</hi> ſo may our people heare it; For the word of the Lord is come forth of your <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and proſpers: Bleſſed be our <hi>Lumen Angliae,</hi> our <hi>Columna literarum,</hi> that ſtands in our Country as a Becon to all, by whom, as a worthy inſtrument, <hi>Deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis
<pb facs="tcp:169752:17"/> haec otia fecit.</hi> Accept of this poore mite, as a gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory Schedule, from my ſelfe in ſpecial to the one of you, and from the Countrey in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to the other of you. And I pray God to move the hearts of more ſuch as may helpe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the worke of the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving friend, and poore labourer in Chriſts Vineyard, W. F.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decemb. 29. 1626.</date> from <hi>Willingſworth.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:18"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169752:18"/>
            <head>Hidden Manna: OR, The Myſtery of Saving Grace.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 25. 14.</bibl>
               <q>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aving grace is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, that no man knowes but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and the Elect cannot know it neither without ſpeciall illumination;</p>
            <p>1. Speciall ſhewing, <hi>Shew me thy wayes O Lord,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169752:19"/> 
               <hi>David.</hi> 2. Barely ſhewing will not ſerve the turne, but there muſt be a ſpeciall teaching, <hi>And teach me thy paths,</hi> ver. 4. 3. Bare teaching will not availe neither, but there muſt be a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall inculcative teaching; <hi>Teach me in the wayes,</hi> to verſ. 8. 4. Inculcative teaching will not doe the deed neither, but there muſt be a ſpeciall directive teaching, <hi>Guide in judgement and teach,</hi> ver. 9. Directive teaching will not be ſufficient neither, but there muſt be a ſpeciall Manu-ductive teaching, <hi>Lead me forth in thy truth, and teach me,</hi> verſ. 5. 6. Manu-ductive teaching will not be effectuall, but there muſt be alſo a ſpeciall choiſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a determinating of the very will; an elective teaching, <hi>Him will he teach the way that he ſhall chuſe,</hi> verſ. 12. And what ſecret is this? not common grace, for that is not the ſecret of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169752:19"/> the Elect, but ſpeciall and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Grace; 1. The ſpeciall grace of Prayer, <hi>Unto thee O Lord I lift up my ſoule,</hi> verſ. 1. 2. A ſpeciall grace of faith, <hi>My God, I truſt in thee,</hi> verſ. 2. 3. A ſpeciall grace of repentance, <hi>Remember not the ſinnes of my youth,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 7. 4. A ſpeciall grace of hope, <hi>My hope is in thee,</hi> verſ. 21. 5. A ſpeciall grace of continuall living in Gods ſight, and dependance upon God, <hi>Mine eyes are ever toward the Lord,</hi> verſ. 15. 6. Which is the roote of all Gods ſpeciall and eternall favour and mercy; <hi>Remember O Lord thy tender mercy, and thy loving kindneſſes for they have been for ever,</hi> v. 6. even Gods ſpeciall mercy to him in particular, verſ. 11. This is the ſecret, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his covenant;</hi> That is, the ſecret
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169752:20"/> favour and grace of the Lord is with them that feare him, and not only with them, but with none elſe, as <hi>Kimchi</hi> ſpeakes; The<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Greeke tranſlates it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The Lord is a ſtrength to thoſe that feare him; but as a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divine notes upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> out of the Hebrew, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, for God hath hid theſe things from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and hath revealed them unto babes.</hi> Whence we gather this point of doctrine; <hi>That ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace that the Children of God have, is a ſecret that none in the world know beſides;</hi> ſo ſaith the Wiſe man, <hi>Froward people are abomination to the Lord, but his ſecret is with the righteous,</hi> Prov. 3. 32. even the ſecret of heavenly grace, which he hath hid from the wiſe and prudent, ſaith St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> yea the very badge of this ſecret <hi>Job</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169752:20"/> calls a ſecret, <hi>The ſecret of God was upon my tabernacle,</hi> Job 29. 4. this is the hidden Manna that the godly eate, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. hidden in a pot of Gold in the Arke, that is, Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. This is the white ſtone, and a new name written in it, which no man knowes of, ſaving him that<note place="margin">Mos erat antiquis ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veis utriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lapillis his damnare rcos, illis abſolvere culpâ. l. 15. metam.</note> receiveth it, <hi>Revelations</hi> 2. 17. whereby the Children of God are abſolved from the wrath to come; a phraſe taken from the Heathen, that uſed to condemne Malefactors with black Stones, and for others with white Stones, as <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpeakes; this therefore is that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſaving pardoning ſecret that no man knowes but he that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it, and therefore the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are called, Gods ſecret ones, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. 3. This ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret is called a ſecret three wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Secret to the eye of ſole
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169752:21"/> nature, and thus it is not meant, for ſo the grace of Chriſt is a ſecret only to Heathens, and ſuch as are as blinde as they, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chriſtians know it, the rine of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secret to the eye of taught nature, nor thus is it meant, for ſo the grace of Chriſt is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret only to the ignorant ſort of Chriſtians, many carnall Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers that ſit under a good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery know it, and the barke of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Secret to the eye of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned nature, and thus it is meant; for ſo the grace of Chriſt is a ſecret to all unſanctified pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, whether learned or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, namely, the pith of it: for though great Doctors, and profound Clerkes, and deepe ſtudied Divines unconverted, know the doctrine of grace, and the truth of grace; though they can diſpute of grace, and talke of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169752:21"/> the glory of grace, yea and taſte a little the good word of grace, yea and underſtand it generally, it may be, as well as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Judas</hi> did, yet the ſpeciall and the ſpirituall knowledge thereof, for all their dogmaticall illumination is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret unto them, thus <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant,</hi> and that for three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon is taken <hi>a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ rei intelligendae,</hi> from the nature of this ſecret, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called a myſtery, a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery kept ſecret, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 25. The wiſdome of God is a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, even the hidden myſtery, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 7. The myſtery of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 1. The myſtery made knowne unto me, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 3. The myſtery of Chriſt, verſ. 4. The myſtery hid in God, ver. 9. The myſtery hid, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 26. a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169752:22"/> rich glorious myſtery, verſ. 27. The myſtery of faith in a pure conſcience, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 13. 9. Yea the Goſpel, though fleſhly men may learne and preach it, yet the ſaving knowledge of it is a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that none but Gods Saints knowes the myſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 19. Yea though the Trinity be knowne unto the wicked, yet none but Gods children know it <hi>piâ cognitione,</hi> piouſly, and therefore that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a myſtery, The myſtery of God, and the Father, and Chriſt, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 2. Yea Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion though the wicked notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally underſtand it, aſſentingly beleeve it, yet indeed it is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret that none but the godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and therefore called a myſtery, even the myſtery of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 3. The Articles of faith, albeit the wicked can ſay them by rote, and credit them univerſally, as for example; the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169752:22"/> Reſurrection, yet none but the holy ones truly beleeve it, and therefore it is called a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 51. The Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, though the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked feele them; and perceive them, yet none but the heires of Heaven truly enjoy them, and therefore they are called a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>The myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed,</hi> Revel. 10. 7. Popery, howſoever the wicked Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſome of them know it, and the policy of it, yet none but Gods marked ones ſee it, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the myſtery of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is called a myſtery, the myſtery of iniquity, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 7. the very Devill himſelfe that would be worſhipped as God, would have his myſteries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> too, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſeus,</hi> unutterable myſteries; Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> compares the myſtery of Chriſt in regard of the wicked to a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169752:23"/> written booke, that the ignorant can neither read, nor ſpell, he ſees the cover, the leaves, and the letters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he underſtands not the meaning of what he ſees; he compares the myſtery of Grace to an indited Epiſtle, which an unskilfull I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deot viewing, he cannot read it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he knoweth it is Paper, and Inke, but the ſence he perceiveth not; ſo the wicked never ſo learned, they perceive the barke of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Chriſt, but not the inward ſence of the Spirit, as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaid of the Philoſophers <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. they are like ſinging Parrots, that can imitate mans voyce, but they skil not the meaning; ſo the wicked can ſpeake gracious things by rote, and underſtand not what they ſpeake; no, that is a ſecret; <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him; and he will</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169752:23"/> 
               <hi>ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is taken <hi>a modo intelligendi,</hi> from the manner of perceiving the ſecret of grace, which is Spirituall; the Naturall man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he know them, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. and he that doth know the minde of the Lord, that is, the ſecret, he muſt have the minde of Chriſt <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Indeed the wicked that have learning may perceive and know theſe things of the Spirit, but they know them in a Carnall manner, not in a ſpirituall wiſe; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they may reforme their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward courſes, and cut off many acts of ſin, and like Grace ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in their hearts; thus farre, and further may the carnall man go, being but changed, not renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now they cannot ſpiritually diſcerne Grace, for in regard of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169752:24"/> ſpirituall diſcerning they are in the darke, even as eyes, ſaith the ſame Father <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even as eyes if they would ſee without light, the eye-ſight, and the goodneſſe, and excellency of the ball wil not avail to make them ſee; ſo the wicked even the learnedſt of them all, they cannot ſee grace becauſe they have the ſpirit of diſcerning light, their learning, and their wit, and all their good parts cannot ſuffice them to deſcry this ſecret; they ſee it indeed, <hi>But ſeeing ſee not, and hearing heare not, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving underſtand not,</hi> Matth. 13. 13. Why the knowledge of this ſecret is not given to them, but only to Chriſts Diſciples, ver. 11. and therefore it is called the Unction of the Holy Ghoſt; yee have an Unction from the Holy one, and ye know all things, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 20. That is, you know all the ſecret, it is called eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169752:24"/> 
               <hi>Anoint thine eyes with eye-ſalve that thou mayeſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſee,</hi> Revel. 3 18. This ſame eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve, the Phyſitians tell us, is an oyntment to purge away all filth and fluxes, and ophthalmies out of the eyes that they may clearly ſee. Its called the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eyes, <hi>Open thou mine eyes, that I may ſee the wondrous things of thy Law,</hi> Pſal. 119. 18. Its called the lighting of the eyes, <hi>Lighten mine eyes,</hi> Pſal. 13. 3. Its called ſeeing, becauſe all the wicked are blinde to this ſecret, <hi>And the eyes of the blinde ſhall ſee out of darkneſſe,</hi> Eſa. 29. 18. Alas, the naturall walkes in the blinde ſhadow of death, and is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this gracious light; no, that is a ſecret, <hi>And the ſecret of the Lord, is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:169752:25"/>
            <p>The third reaſon is taken <hi>a ſtatu intelligentis,</hi> from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the party that muſt perceive the ſecret of grace, he muſt have another ſecret thing to be made capable of this ſecret, and that is the new creature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 15. which is called the hidden man of the heart, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4. Its called a hidden life, <hi>Your life is hid with Chriſt in God,</hi> Col. 3. 3. and therefore the word of God is cloſed up in the godly, that the wicked underſtand it not, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 9, 10. they are like ſcrauled blotted papers that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive. The Law is ſealed up in the godlies heart, and the ungodly, whether learned or unlearned cannot read it, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29. 11, 12. Seale my Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my diſciples, <hi>Eſa. 8. 16. A garden incloſed is my ſiſter, my ſpouſe, aſpring ſhut up, a fountain ſealed,</hi> Cant. 4. 12. That is <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the myſtery ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169752:25"/> even the ſigned and ſealed myſtery of faith and grace; for as a private letter to a friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſecret matter that no man elſe may read, becauſe it is ſealed; ſo is grace ſealed up, it is under the Privy-ſeale of heaven, that no man can breake open, but the faithfull, to whom it is ſent. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is revealed to them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>My firſt uſe ſhall be for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</q>
            <p>Is Gods ſecret with them that feare him? then the godly are the friends of God, <hi>Yee are my friends, if you doe whatſoever I command you,</hi> Joh. 15. 14. <hi>Henceforth I call you not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, for the ſervant knoweth not what his Lord doth, but I have called you friends, for I have made all things knowne unto you,</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>Myſteriis digni facti eſtis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theophy lact,</hi> I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169752:26"/> have thought you worthy to bee acquainted with my ſecrets, and <hi>Abraham</hi> was called the friend of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 23. What ſhall I hide from my friend? <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham the thing that I doe,</hi> Gen. 18. 17? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> Oh how greatly God condeſcends to the godly! hee ſpeakes to them as a man would ſpeake to his friend; there is no profitable ſecret that he will not impart unto them, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew to them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Is Gods ſecret with them that feare him?</hi> then the godly are all one with God: As <hi>Oreſtes</hi> and <hi>Pylades</hi> loved one another ſo well, that they were all one with another: <hi>Oreſtes</hi> was called <hi>Pylades,</hi> and <hi>Pylades</hi> was called <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> ſo are the godly all one with each other; St. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169752:26"/> calls the godly Chriſt, yea Chriſt ſaith as much, <hi>That they all may be one as thou Father art in me; and I in thee, that they alſo may bee one in us,</hi> Joh. 17. 21. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> ſo far forth as its poſſible for man to be one with God; ſo here the honour of the godly, they are admitted to Gods ſecrets to be one with him. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius Caeſar</hi> thought no man fit to know his ſecrets, and yet the Lord vouchſafeth the godly his owne ſecrets, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> could tell the ſecrets that were ſpoken in the Kings bed-chamber, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6. 12. ſo the godly know the ſecrets of Gods cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, even of the King of Kings Preſence-chamber. O the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the godly, ſaith a ſweet Father againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> none but Noble-men, Lords and Dukes might be made partakers of State-ſecrets, they eſteemed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169752:27"/> ſecrecie a God-head, a divine thing, ſaith <hi>Ammianus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus,</hi> the godly are heavenly Lords, and Nobles, and the Privy-ſtates-men of heavens Court, <hi>Such honour have all his Saints,</hi> for the Kings ſecrets are the glory of the ſubject that is in favour, ſaith <hi>Caſſiodore,</hi> and the Lords ſecrets are the glory of the godly. <hi>The ſecrets of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>My ſecond uſe ſhall be for Refutation.</q>
            <p>Away then with <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Semi-pelagians,</hi> and <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans,</hi> what ſhall I call them? <hi>Scabioſum teſſerula<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> far poſſidet.</hi> their griſt is all muſty that ſay, God gives no ſecret thing to any one man more then another, that rifle up all Gods ſecrets, and would have all men ſo many <hi>Tireſiaſes</hi> that ſwallow up St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as it were a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169752:27"/> depthleſſe depth. St. <hi>Paul</hi> cryes out, <hi>Oh how unſearchable,</hi> Rom. 11. 33. Oh how ſecret are theſe things! and theſe <hi>Numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Coſmongers,</hi> pick-lock Gods ſecret cloſet, and expoſe his hidden treaſures; St. <hi>Paul</hi> he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Who hath knowne?</hi> verſ. 34. who hath knowne theſe ſecrets? <hi>Arminius vol Comma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genus Aruſpex pectora divo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum rimatur, &amp; exta,</hi> as <hi>Juve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> the Satyriſt ſpeakes; let me tranſlate it: <hi>Arminius</hi> and his company ranſack all Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, divulge and communicate them to the ſeed of the woman, and of the Serpent all alike, they make Gods eternall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> love of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, no ſecret, but a vulgar Idea, they make the myſtery of Chriſt, and him crucified, no ſecret, but like an Apothecaries drug, Catholicall, they make the eſpeciall grace of God, no ſecret, but a common quality; faith no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169752:28"/> ſecret, but a general vertue; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and the new creature, no ſecret, but a univerſall gift, no ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret favour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but make God a party <hi>ante,</hi> not to love St. <hi>Peter</hi> more then <hi>Judas;</hi> no ſecret intent to any one perſon more then another; but that Chriſt might have dyed for all him, and never a man ſaved; no ſecret working of the Lord in any more then other, but for any thing that either God the Father hath done by creating<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God the Son by redeeming, or God the Holy Ghoſt by ſanctifying, all the world were left to their ſcrambling, take it, if you will, if you will not, chuſe; they ſay God would have men to be ſaved, but that hee will not worke it for his owne part, rather for this man, or that man deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minately that he be ſaved, as <hi>Stilpo</hi> ſayd that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, man is no man, an univerſall is never a man, for its neither this man, nor
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169752:28"/> that man, for why not this man, as well as that man? ſo ſay they, Chriſt dyed for man, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for no man, not this, nor that man; for why rather this man, then that man, or that man, more then this man? <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and all the Saints might<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Man, in regard of Gods grace, is like <hi>Pontilian, Saepe ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus nunquam prior ipſe ſalutas; ſic crit aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Pontiliane, vale.</hi> Martial. <hi>l. 5. Ep.</hi> 67. He was often ſaluted firſt, but he never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt, ſo that he gave a continuall farewell. So God often prevents man, but man never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents him firſt; and were it not for God he would give an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall farewell too all grace.</note> have been damned for all God, and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Ahab,</hi> and curſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> might have beene ſaved, and not they, for all him; no ſecret refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God in this man, rather then that man; but bleſſed <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> in heaven, is no more bound unto God, then damned <hi>Dives</hi> in hell, <hi>Nun quis te diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crevit?</hi> No ſecret putting a difference betwixt Angel or Devil, but if <hi>David</hi> be better then <hi>Saul,</hi> he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169752:29"/> may ſacrifice to his owne net: Thus theſe heretical Opinioniſts, ſchimatical Quodlibetiſts; ſo I may call them, are worſe then the Roman blabs that <hi>Paulus</hi> the Lawyer ſpeaks of, that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed ſecrets, for they cut off all Gods ſecrets at one blow. But we, beloved we, let us hold this as a foundation, <hi>For the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God remaineth ſure, and hath this ſeale, the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 19. The foundation is faith, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks, and as a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is ſecret under God, ſo is faith ſecretly grounded in the hearts of thoſe that are Gods. This ſeale is Gods confirming grace, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and as a ſeale is ſet upon ſecrets, ſo is this grace ſecretly radicated, and abiding in them; this <hi>Knowing,</hi> the Lord knoweth who are his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the ſecret election of God, ſaith <hi>Haymo;</hi> as if the Apoſtle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169752:29"/> ſhould ſay, though <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> and ſuch like were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> without ſeale, and erred concerning the Faith, and fell off from what they ſeemed to have. Nevertheleſſe Gods ſecret is with his, the foundation of God is ſure, and hath this ſeale, the Lord knoweth who are his; <hi>For the ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>My third uſe ſhall bee for Conſolation.</q>
            <p>Oh what incomparable comfort is this to Gods people! Gods ſecret is with them, God hath, and will reveale his ſecret myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries unto them, God hath given them a proſpective Chinke to looke by into his ſecret things; they are Gods friends, and as they turn my Text in meeter, they know Gods ſecret intent, they are ſo honoured with the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169752:30"/> God hides no good thing from them which is neceſſary for their ſalvation. All the earth is Gods, but ſuch as obey Gods voice are Gods peculiar treaſure, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 5. Gods ſpeciall jewells, <hi>Segullah</hi> it is in the originall, that is Gods proper ones, or Gods ſecret ones that he keeps in ſtore for himſelfe, and for eſpecial uſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Greeke turnes it, like a jewell which the King delivers not into the hands of any of his officers, but keepes himſelfe in ſecret, ſaith <hi>Rabbi Menahim,</hi> he hath choſen them to be a ſpeciall people to himſelfe above all people that are upon the face of the earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 6. that is a ſecret people, <hi>A choſen generation, a royall Prieſthood, a holy Nation, a peculiar people, 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 9. that is a ſecret Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his peculiar pearle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135. 4. that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſecret gem, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omfort, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169752:30"/> God gives them ſome ſpeciall peculiar ſecret grace that he gives to none elſe in the world but to them. Chriſt hath given himſelfe for them <hi>That he might redeem them from all iniquity, and purge to himſelfe a peculiar people, zealous of good workes, Tit.</hi> 2. 14. that is a ſecret gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. God loves a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and a ſpeciall claime to them, as <hi>Syneſius</hi> uſeth the word, for to them alone he maketh known the myſtery of his will according to his good pleaſure, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 9. even his ſecret will, and hidden plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They are Gods portion, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 9. The lot of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, as a great inheritor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in ſome ſecret boxe, or ſome ſecret cloſet his bonds and writings, he keeps them ſecretly under locke and key; ſo are the godly. Oh what a bleſſed and happy eſtate is the eſtate of all that feare God! Doſt thou ſerve
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169752:31"/> God in thy family? Doſt thou ſerve him in thy calling? Doſt thou ſtand to his truth openly, and indeare it above all riches privately? Doſt thou make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of every of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements? feare not, the Lords ſecret is with thee, there is no evill ſhall ever hurt thy ſoule; <hi>For in the time of trouble hee ſhall hide thee in his pavilion, in the ſecret of his tabernacle, ſhall he hide thee, and ſhall ſet thee upon a rocke,</hi> Pſal. 27. 5. Doe the proud inſult over thee? Doe the wicked tongues nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name thee? <hi>God ſhall hide thee in the ſecret of his preſence from the pride of man, God ſhall keep thee ſecretly in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilion from the ſtrife of tongues,</hi> Pſal. 31. 20. Gods grace is a ſpeciall grace to ſuch as you are, and ſuch as you are onely. Chriſt Jeſus is your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for hee will ſave his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169752:31"/> people, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21. This ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome is a ſpeciall ranſome, a ranſome not for all, but for many, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 28. His bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding was a ſpeciall bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding, not for all, but for you many, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 28. Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is a ſpeciall ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not of all, but of you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 19. Juſtification is a ſpeciall juſtification, not of all, but of you onely, his elect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 33. Interceſſion is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall interceſſion, not for all, but for you alone, <hi>verſ.</hi> 34. Chriſt is the head, a ſpirituall head, not to all, but to you his Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 22. Chriſt his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing was a ſpecial purchaſing, not of all, but of you his Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 28. Chriſt his prayer is a ſpecial prayer, not for all, but for you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 9. Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption was a ſpecial redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not of all, but of you that are his ſonnes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. Chriſt is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169752:32"/> the authour of a ſpecial ſalvation, not to all in general, but to all you that obey him, <hi>Heb. 5. 9. Specialiter,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> eſpecially for you, whom hee hath made with himſelfe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires of ſalvation. It is a ſecret that God hath given you, none of the wicked in all the world know it, it is a ſecret favour that he hath vouchſafed you, no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, nor drunkard, ſcrape-pelfe, nor ſwearer, nor any ungodly man, or woman in the earth partaketh of it with you.</p>
            <p>Be comforted, then whoſoever thou art, that haſt given over thy wicked wayes, and betaken thy ſelfe to newneſſe of life, <hi>For the ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay, Alas, thou canſt not pray, thou canſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, thou canſt not ſerve God!</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169752:32"/>
            <p>I anſwer, Though theſe things do not openly manifeſt themſelves, yet Gods ſeed may abide in thee, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 9. Seed is ſecret in the ground, and ſeemes to be hid, yet it ſprouts out in its time; and groweth; ſo grace may be as hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſeed in thy heart, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſowne in thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt object againe, Alas, I cannot feele any ſuch matter!</p>
            <p>I anſwer, what if thou canſt not, it may bee ſecret as from others, ſo from thine owne ſenſe and feeling, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>My fourth uſe ſhall be for Terror to the wicked.</q>
            <p>Here's horror to all the ungodly, they are ſtrangers from God, they are not admitted unto Gods ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets. The godly are ſigned with the Spirit, ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169752:33"/> ſecret <hi>obſignatum,</hi> Gods Spirit is their Sigil, ſaith <hi>Theodoret,</hi> a ſecret ſeale, they are his ſonnes, and ſealed with his Spirit, ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> a ſecret Son-ſhip. But the wicked have neither ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſigne, nor ſecret ſeale, nor ſecret Son-ſhip, nor any ſecret ſpecial or peculiar thing of God, they are aliens from God; <hi>Reveale not thy ſecrets to a ſtranger,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales not his ſecrets to ſuch as are ſtrangers to him. As <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> ſaid of his <hi>Acroamatiks,</hi> that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſet out, but not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſet forth; ſo may I ſay of the Law, and the Goſpel in regard of the wicked, it is expreſſed, but not expounded to them; now when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliouſly reject all obedience, he will cloſe their eyes, and hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winke both wicked Miniſters and people, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 29. 10. Yea the Pſalmiſt curſeth them that their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169752:33"/> eyes be darkned that they ſee not, <hi>Pſal. 69. 23. Poure out thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation upon them, and let thy wrathfull anger take hold of them,</hi> verſ. 24. As if hee ſhould ſay, <hi>ipſiſſimam perditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Marlorat,</hi> let them be damned, and all with damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, for Gods wayes are kept ſecret from them, and not with them. Art thou a drunkard, and haſt not Gods ſecret to keepe thee from drunkenneſſe? here thou feeſt thou art in the ſtate of damnation: Art thou a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and haſt not Gods ſecret to keep thee from worldlineſſe? thou art in the ſtate of damnation: Art thou malicious, and a hater of thy brother; and haſt not Gods ſecret to keep thee from it? thou art in the ſtate of damnation? Art thou a ſweater, a lyar, or a luke-warmling &amp;c. and haſt not Gods ſecret to keepe thee from thy ſinnes? thou art in the Jawes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169752:34"/> of Hell and vengeance, <hi>brut us ſtupor</hi> as <hi>Calvin.</hi> ſpeakes, a brutiſh ſtupidity poſſeſſeth thee, the ſecret of the Devill is with thee, thou haſt thy ſecret too, but it is the Devils ſecret; thou keepeſt the Devils counſell. <hi>O my ſoule, come not thou into their ſecret,</hi> Gen: 49. 6. Well may ſome be called the Devils ſecret, for the Devill hath power over the wicked ſecretly, and they perceive it not; the ſecret counſell of the wicked, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 64. 2. The ſecret of mockers, ſo it is in the Originall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 17. as for the ſecret of the Lord, that is with them that feare him, <hi>nemini niſi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> with none elſe; <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the grace of Gods Children ſuch a ſecret that none in the world knoweth beſides them?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169752:34"/> then let me commit this to the <hi>Arminians</hi> conſideration, what miſchiefe he doth to his owne ſoule; God ſaith this grace is a ſecret thing, only revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to his ſecret ones; God ſaith, it is a myſtery opened only to thoſe that are his; God ſaith, it muſt be ſpiritually diſcerned, and without a ſpeciall eye-ſalve can never be perceived; God ſaith, it is a fountaine ſealed up from the men of this world, a booke claſped up, that nor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor unlearned can read, but only they to whom it is eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given from above; God ſaith, it is a depth, it is unſearchable, and a peculiar treaſure, a peculiar pearle, a ſpeciall gift; but the <hi>Arminian</hi> lookes for no other grace but what is not ſecret, not peculiar, not ſpeciall, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon grace; he lookes for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace ſave that which God vouchſafeth to all, even repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169752:35"/> and all. Oh what and if this Metaphyſicall grace they hazzard their ſoules upon, ſhould prove uneffectuall, I beſeech theſe men to chew upon this point; I doe not ſay they doe debarre them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Salvation, but if they would ruminate this thing ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, I thinke they would not dye as they doe for ten thouſand worlds; let them heare a little, and I pray let their Conſciences intently ponder.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Muſt it be a ſecret grace of God that the world hath not, if a man be the childe of God? Oh then (I quake to thinke of it) how doe they looke to be the Children of God only with their univerſall Grace?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Muſt it be a ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that a man muſt have if he be redeemed? how doe they looke to be redeemed with a generall?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Muſt God give faith in a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169752:35"/> ſpecially manner, or elſe a man cannot beleeve? how doe they looke for faith by an univerſall gift?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Muſt a man have a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar grace, or elſe he cannot be of the redeemed of the Lord, how doe they looke for it that doe not ſo much as pray for it by their tenent?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Muſt a man be beholding to<note place="margin">They ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute God with thankes by the halves like as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius</hi> ſaluted <hi>Decimus</hi> by the name of <hi>Quixtus, Mart. l. 4. Epig. 22.</hi>
               </note> God in a ſpeciall manner, if he be choſen out of the world? Oh how doe they looke to be vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, that profeſſe themſelves not ſo much as to conne God any thankes for it?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Muſt a man be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately converted to God in his will of God, or elſe he cannot be converted? how doe they look for it that profeſſe they doe not looke for it from God, but from their owne freedome?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Muſt Chriſt pray in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall wiſe for thoſe that are his,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169752:36"/> that their wills may be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">As <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> called <hi>Cinna Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minus,</hi> when he meant no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 5 Ep. 58. ſo theſe men call God Lord, whereas they mean no ſuch matter, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Lords over their owne hearts.</note> how doe they looke to have the will and the deed, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly maintaine, that they will not be beholding to Chriſt for his prayers no further, but to have the power of will; yea, and that Chriſt muſt pray them, if he meane to have the will it ſelf, that doe even diſpute the caſe, contend, and give out in effect, that there is no ſpeciall prayer, nor ſpeciall quickning, they will not acknowledge any ſecret mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, yea they write, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly doe they reaſon it too, that if God doe no more to them <hi>a priori</hi> then to the vildeſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Caſt-away, give them meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Catholique <hi>poſſe</hi> without any ſpeciall <hi>eſſe,</hi> yet they can be ſaved. They ſay that they can beleeve, that they can repent, that they can be converted is from God; but that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that they doe repent, that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169752:36"/> they are converted, is from the liberty of their owne wills; <hi>But what haſt thou that thou haſt not received? and if thou haſt received it, why boaſteſt thou as if thou hadſt not received,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 7.? Well, I will tell thee, if thou boaſteſt thus, ſure I am thou haſt not received it; but thou wilt ſay, as <hi>Cornelius à Lapide,</hi> That I doe beleeve, that I doe repent, that I am conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is from mine owne will, but I received the power of God, and I doe it by the vertue of that grace which I received of God. Nay, but oh man, the very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting and drawing of this act from that which thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, cannot be without a ſpeciall act of God; for the wicked that have received ſo farre, yea having received further, even this ſecret too, doe not beleeve, doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, are not converted. Thou beleeveſt thou repenteſt, and not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169752:37"/> 
               <hi>Judas,</hi> and not <hi>Elimas,</hi> Doſt thou? well then, either St. <hi>Paul</hi> is a lyar, or thou muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived more then an univerſall grace, or elſe thou art a lyar, thou beleeveſt not, thou repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt not, thou art not converted; Of what boaſteſt thou ſaith <hi>Theodoret,</hi> of thine eloquence? but God gave it thee: of thy knowledge, but God conferred it on thee, he might goe on of thy power of beleeving, but it is the gift of God; of the deed it ſelfe, but it is the worke of God; of any one ſtock of good that God ſhould joyne with thee upon it, but that was the effect of God too. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> thou ſayeſt hath Free-will, and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> hath the ſame: Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had power of God to beleeve, and <hi>Judas</hi> hath the ſame; Thus farre God goeth along (thou ſayeſt) with <hi>Judas</hi> as well as with <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169752:37"/> and hath faith it ſelfe, and <hi>Judas</hi> hath not; and what now ſay I (and yet not I, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) hath St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that he hath not received? and if he have received it, how can Saint <hi>Peter</hi> boaſt, that he hath not received, no more then <hi>Judas,</hi> that hath not received at all? Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> have both Free-will of God, there they agree; Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> have both power of God to beleeve, there they agree too; thou ſayeſt, <hi>Judas</hi> doth not beleeve, St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth, there they differ; And who made thee <hi>Peter</hi> to differ from <hi>Judas?</hi> Certainly when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> asked the queſtion, <hi>Who hath made thee differ from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 7. he never thought the queſtion could, or ſhould be ſo anſwered, that thine owne will made thee differ from another. Take heed, O man, ſhall a Begger ſtand at the doore
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169752:38"/> and tell thee, he doth not ſtand in need of this, or that almes, but can help himſelfe well enough, without receiving ought from thee; wouldſt thou help him? I trow not to ſuch a boaſting Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Alas poore Mendicant! and<note place="margin">Like <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulla,</hi> that having gotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers hair, ſwore it was her own haire, <hi>Martial.</hi> l. 6 <hi>Ep.</hi> 12. like <hi>Fidentinus,</hi> that repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> bookes for his owne, 1 <hi>Ep. 30.</hi>
               </note> how doeſt thou looke for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>credere,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reſipiſcere</hi> for the Almes of actuall faith, and repentance at Gods mercy gate, and be at theſe termes with God? This is to deale with God as concerning grace, as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> for the watering of their Country, they ſaid they were not bound to the gods for it, but to <hi>Nilus.</hi> So thou ſayeſt, by this Opinion thou art not bound to God for it, but to the freedome of thy will; no, the Pſalmiſt reads us another Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him.</hi> Tremble then O duſt and aſhes, to diſanull Gods ſecrets: ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169752:38"/> thou make ſome mens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets no ſecrets, but ſhouldeſt commonly ſpread them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus,</hi> Thou ſhouldeſt have thy tongue cut out; O what a fearefull ſinne doeſt thou run into, if thou doſt diſplay the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Lord of Heaven on this faſhion? Doſt not thou read of Gods ſpeciall grace every where in Scripture, before thou canſt read of any good in any man or woman? As it was ſaid of <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> that he got his<note place="margin">Pherecydes.</note> learning by the <hi>Phaenycean</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, ſo thou mayeſt finde in Holy Writ, that all the Elect got all that they had from Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſecret, even his ſpeciall and ſecret grace; <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah</hi> were faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid of God, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhall breake the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head;</hi> Gen. 3. 15? not—him, ſo as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169752:39"/> might, if they would breake the Serpents head; no, he ſhall breake it, is a word <hi>de facto, He ſhall breake the Serpents head; Seth</hi> was faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid, <hi>God had appointed him,</hi> Gen. 4. 25. and not <hi>Caine? Noah</hi> was faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid, before he heard one ſillable of good in <hi>Noah,</hi> Noah <hi>found grace in Gods ſight,</hi> Gen. 6. 8. and not others? <hi>Abraham</hi> was faithfull, but had not God firſt called him? <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 1. and not the reſt that were in <hi>Ur</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees? Iſaac</hi> was faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid, <hi>In</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy ſeed be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> and not in <hi>Iſhmael? Jacob</hi> was faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid, <hi>I have loved Jacob,</hi> and not <hi>Eſau?</hi> Rom. 9. <hi>David</hi> was faithfull, but was it not firſt ſaid, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord came upon David?</hi> 1 Sam. 16. 13. <hi>Job</hi> was faithfull, but doth not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169752:39"/> the very Devil acknowledge Gods ſpeciall bleſſing to him firſt? <hi>Job 1. 10, &amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſerves all this? but to teach thee how to beware, leſt thou ſinne againſt Gods ſpeciall ſecret, O the Lord will not ſuffer this indignity at thine hands, as to abuſe his ſecrets; even the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in Hell, that are called Gods Apes, among the <hi>Paynims,</hi> they would have their ſecrets invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably preſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dionyſius Haelicarnaſſeus</hi> tels us of the <hi>Pinarii Arcano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cuſtodes,</hi> that looked to the ſecrets: and verily the ſacred Lord of unſearchable glory is tender of his ſecret. Conſider how wretchedly thou wrongeſt thy Maker, in ſaying, the reaſon why one is converted and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, is from the free arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Will, for thou rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſt God of his ſecret jewell, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord</hi> ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169752:40"/> the ſecret of the Will, ſo it ſhould be, ſayeſt thou; that is, the ſecret cauſe why this man is converted rather then ſome other. I beſeech thee quake, and dare not ſo great audacity. Is not mans Will ſaid every where to be paſſive, and all to magnifie this ſecret? Are not the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God ſaid to be elected, called, converted, redeemed, juſtified, adopted, ſanctified? Are not their Wills ſaid to be turned, mollified? All paſſive, all to ſhew, all to be from this ſecret. Thou that art an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaller of Grace anſwer me, Why was <hi>Jonas</hi> ſent to <hi>Niniveh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionas 1.</note> and not to <hi>Tarſus?</hi> why was <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> ſent to the widow of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptah,</hi> when there were other widowes in <hi>Iſrael</hi> as well as ſhe? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17. was it not of this ſecret? Why was <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to goe to <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and not <hi>Bythinia?</hi> Acts 16. 7.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169752:40"/> was it not from this ſecret? Why hath ſuch and ſuch Countries meanes of Salvation, and others againe for many hundred, nay thouſand of yeares not? was it not from this ſecret? Why are ſome Aufes and Fools like beaſts in knowledge to their dying day, and others not, is it not from this ſecret? Againe, anſwer me; Wherefore were all almoſt that were converted in Scripture then converted, when their owne wils were about no ſuch matter, but rather the cleane contrary, but only to ſet up this ſecret? <hi>Pauls</hi> will was to perſecute Grace, then did he light upon converſion of grace, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. was it not from this ſecret? <hi>Levi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> when he was ſitting at the grating receipt of Cuſtome, then he roſe to the receipt of grace, <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. 14. was it not from this ſecret? Were it from the liberty of the Will, then converſion ſhould be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169752:41"/> when the Will is moſt intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; wherefore was the man, poſſeſſed with a Legion of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, turned in the inſtant, could that be from the firſt choyſe of his owne Wil? <hi>Mar.</hi> 5. 2. nay, he cryed out againſt Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 7. but even then was he converted, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. was it not from this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret? Wherefore are Publicans and Harlots oftner ſaved then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther orderlyer people, is it not from this ſecret? wherefore was<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero's</hi> harlot.</note> that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls her, and not <hi>Seneca?</hi> was it not ſtill from this ſecret? Againe anſwer me, Why is not every bleſſing of God uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, if Saving Grace were to be univerſall? God doth not give ſtrength to all, nor beauty to all, nor wit to all, nor riches to all, nor houſes to all, nor learning to all, nor any left hand favour to all, and will he give Saving Grace to all? Shall we deny that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169752:41"/> to God which we account an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to offer a deniall of to the meaneſt of Gods Creatures? May not a Mother love one childe more then another, yea while they are conſidered in themſelves both alike? May not a Maſter love one of his ſervants more then another, though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected alike? May not a Prince raiſe up a Favourite out of the reſt of the people, though circumſtantiated alike? Yea ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fowles love ſome young one more then another, though qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified alike; yea the very Viper will affect one of her brood more then the reſt, though ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped alike; The Sunne doth not ſhine upon all places alike, nor the Moone upon all corners alike; the Mother Earth doth not feed all her Plants alike, but ſome more, ſome leſſe, ſome not at all. And wilt thou ſay that God gives univerſall grace alike, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169752:42"/> deny him to doe with his owne whatſoever he pleaſeth? The Pſalmiſt here teacheth yee better Divinity, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> O remember, it is the part of a ſlanderer to diſcover ſecrets, <hi>Prov. 11. 13. Prov.</hi> 20. 19. and verily thou ſlandereſt Gods wiſe and hidden Counſels, that thus broacheſt all his ſecrets; yea, thou takeſt part with mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that revile the Saints, who ſay to the godly; Oh, forſooth, what ſecret have you? oh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like you are of thoſe ſpecial ones; even as <hi>Eliphas</hi> abuſed <hi>Job, Haſt thou heard the ſecret of God? and doſt thou reſtraine wiſdome to thy ſelfe?</hi> Job 15. 8. <hi>What knoweſt thou that we knew not? What underſtandeſt thou that is not in us?</hi> ver. 9. <hi>With us are both the gray-headed, and the aged men, much elder
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169752:42"/> then thy father,</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>Is there any ſecret thing in thee,</hi> verſ. 11? yes mocker, there is a ſecret with them, and God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales it to his babes, and leaves the wiſe and the aged many times in their folly, and it is Gods glory to conceale this ſecret from them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25. 1. not as if the godly can, or may pry into Gods ſecret Arke, but this ſecret is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their owne vildneſſe, which <hi>Zophar</hi> calls the ſecret of wiſdome, <hi>Job</hi> 11. 6. This is a ſecret that God reveals to them alone. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing the grace of converſion is a ſecret, how comes it about then, that the wicked, that have not this ſpeciall ſecret afforded them, are bound to be converted, and ſhall be judged for not being converted?</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169752:43"/>
            <p>For anſwer hereunto, I muſt needs uſe a little extravagancy: The Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Woe be unto thee, O Jeruſalem, wilt thou not be made cleane?</hi> This is a plaine queſtion, and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the people ſhould anſwer yea, or no; ſuppoſe they anſwer downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right No, we will not bee made cleane; then their wilfulneſſe plainly appeares, they will not be made cleane: ſuppoſe they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer Yea, we will be made clean, then their wilfulneſſe appeares to bee double, for they are not onely wilfull, but lyingly wilful; wee will be made cleane, but when ſhall it once be, ſaith God? they doe but dally with him, ſo that he is faine to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce a woe, <hi>Woe unto thee, O Jeruſalem;</hi> and queſtion againe, as being not yet ſatisfied, When ſhall it once be? It is evident then that they were wilful in their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169752:43"/> 
               <hi>They kept not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God, and refuſed to walke in his law,</hi> Pſal. 78. 10. that is, neither did they, nor would they: <hi>The wicked refuſe to doe judgement,</hi> Prov. 21. 7. <hi>They would not heare,</hi> Eſa. 28. 12. <hi>Children that will not heare the law of the Lord,</hi> Eſa. 30. 9. <hi>And they would not,</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>They would not walke in Gods wayes, neither were they obedient to his word,</hi> Eſa. 42. 24. <hi>They would not bee aſhamed, they would not receive correction,</hi> Jer. 5. 3. <hi>They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to returne,</hi> Jer. 8. 5. <hi>They refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the ſhoulder, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their eares that they ſhould not heare,</hi> Zach. 7. 11. So that here wee ſee the wicked are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full againſt converſion: That they are wilfull may bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</p>
            <p>1. From the corrupt nature of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169752:44"/> their will, their heart is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is deadly wicked, ſaith <hi>Buxtorfius, Bonorum expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buxtorf.</note> 
               <hi>nuſquam apparet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mellius,</hi> There is no good to bee expected in it; and therefore as it wils ſin, ſo it will will ſin, and will wil not be converted. <hi>The car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall heart is enmity againſt God, for it is not ſubject to the law of God, neither indeed can bee,</hi> Rom. 8. 7. that is, it doth not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not doe good, but it is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of God, it doth not onely not obey, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it cannot obey, and why can it not? <hi>Quia non vult,</hi> as <hi>Haymo</hi> ſpeakes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it wil not; for [becauſe it can not] is not put as a reaſon of its not obeying, but as a parentheſis, as if he ſhould ſay, It is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Law of God, becauſe it is an enemy, it will not; indeed it is true it cannot, but that's not the reaſon, for it rebels againſt it,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169752:44"/> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23. it will not bee made clean. That they are wilfull may be gathered,</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the abominable ſpawne of hideous conditions in the heart, for a wicked heart is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an alſeminary of ſinnes, an univerſal roe, or ſeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot of rebellions. Tell it of new obedience, it ſimply wills not, <hi>They would not conſider his wayes,</hi> Job 34. 27. urge it, it perverſely wils not, <hi>The ungodly man ſcornes judgement,</hi> Prov. 19. 28. urge it further, it ſtrongly wils not, <hi>A foole rageth, and is careleſſe,</hi> Prov. 14. 16. preſſe yet more, not onely outwardly by preaching, but alſo inwardly, by the ſtrange motions of Gods Spirit, it ſtubbornely and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maciouſly wils not, <hi>They reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Act. 7. 51. winde into it, and excite it, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, and deſperately wils not, <hi>He hath done deſpight unto the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169752:45"/> Spirit of grace,</hi> Heb. 10. 29. their will is the very tunnel of hell it ſelfe, ſo that the ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Spirit is in the bottome of the heart, and the reaſon why all doe not breake forth into it is, <hi>becauſe God doth not follow and preſſe all the wicked hearts alike with grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they are wilful, may be gathered Thirdly, from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their corrupt heart the Devill, <hi>For the devill worketh and ruleth in the children of diſobedience,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 2. It is the devil that poyſoned the heart, and what poyſon hath he brought into the heart? even like a Serpent, the poyſon that he hath in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, namely willingneſſe to diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and wilfulneſſe (either actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally or radically) in diſobeying, and therefore a wicked heart is wilful upon ſinne, <hi>It is dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 1.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169752:45"/> But what death is that that the Apoſtle tels us? a luſtful deſiring ſelfe-minded wilful death, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> this death is an elective death, dead the Will is, and dead would be, <hi>My people love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5. 31. whence I deduce this ſure concluſion, <hi>That the reaſon why wicked men are not conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and doe not repent, is not becauſe they cannot, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not.</hi> The Lord doth not ſay, Canſt thou not bee made clean, But wilt thou not? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a wicked man cannot repent; <hi>For, no man can come unto me except my Father draw him,</hi> Joh. 6. 44. <hi>No man can come unto me except it be given to him of my Father,</hi> verſ. 65. that is, beleeve in me ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> Hence it is, ſaith the ſame Father, that the preaching of the Croſſe is <hi>pereuntibus ſtultitia</hi> to them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169752:46"/> that periſh fooliſhneſſe, but unto them that are ſaved, it is <hi>virtus Dei;</hi> every wicked man is like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> dead in the grave, faſt bound, and a ſtone upon him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it being an<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> impoſſible thing to raiſe himſelfe againe: as a foundered horſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but limp, ſo a wicked heart cannot but be impenitent; there is a neceſſity, though not a violent, yet a cruel neceſſity, as <hi>Avitor</hi> cals it, not as fatal, yet a willing misfree neceſſity, as <hi>Bernard</hi> cals it; So that <hi>Luther</hi> gives the free wil of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man in regard of grace, a good title, <hi>Res de ſolo titulo,</hi> A naked titular thing, no ſuch matter. Yet notwithſtanding, albeit the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keds will canot but be impenitent, the cauſe why it is impenitent, is not becauſe it cannot be otherwiſe, but becauſe it will not be otherwiſe penitent, it doth not repent, and it will not, <hi>Sic volo, ſtat pro ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione voluntas,</hi> ſo I will, this will is the reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169752:46"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Thou wilt ſay, thou wouldeſt repent, although thou bee a wicked man, I would if I could, but alas I cannot, though I would.</p>
            <p>I anſwer three wayes; 1. Haſt thou a will in thee to repent? many will boaſt every one of his owne goodneſſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 6. It may be ſaid to thee, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid to his friend, of a wicked youngſter, that ſaid he would bee good; I do not ſay, ſayes he, he lies, but <hi>put at ſe cupere,</hi> he thinkes he wills, but he wills not. Thou ſayeſt thou haſt a will to repent, whom may I beleeve ſaith St. <hi>Bernard?</hi> truly, I dare not beleeve thee, if thou liveſt in wicked courſes, thou haſt a will to live in them, <hi>Thou art a ſcorner, and wilt heare no rebuke,</hi> Prov. 13. 1. Thou art ſo, and thou wilt bee ſo, thou wilt not be made cleane.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I anſwer, thou ſayeſt thou art offended with thine
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169752:47"/> owne iniquities, I doe not deny it, what damned Devill is not? <hi>Homines vitam ſuam, &amp; amant &amp; oderunt,</hi> wicked men hate their owne lives, and love them both at one time, their owne conſcience gripes them, and ſo they muſt needs finde fault with themſelves, but then their corrupt deſires tranſport them: Thou doſt not will to be wicked, and yet thou doſt will to bee wicked, like old wife <hi>Akko,</hi> that ſaid ſhe would not, and yet ſhee would; Like a Whore that would be ſtrange, forſooth, Oh ſhe will not, and yet it is becauſe ſhe may cogge the more the love of her Paramours. Thou wouldeſt repent, and thou wilt goe on in ſinne, thou haſt a ſetled will to ſinne, but a ſorry would, or a months minde to repent; The truth is, thou calleſt for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, thou prayeſt, thou repenteſt, for a faſhion to humor thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169752:47"/> and ſinne the freelier; <hi>For the ſoule of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wiſheth evill,</hi> Prov. 21. 10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou ſayeſt thou wilt repent: the glutton when hee feeles his head to paine him, his panch to burden him, his belches to annoy him, he will not be ſuch a glutton againe; what ſaith the Stoicke? <hi>Stomachum illi fecit luxuria, cito tamen redibit in gratiam,</hi> his gluttony hath turned his ſtomach a little, hee'l bee friends with his ſinne next time againe. The wicked Iſraelites they ſought God, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired early after the Lord for a while, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 34. but how long did it hold? Alas, <hi>Their heart was not right within them, they would not abide his Covenant,</hi> verſ. 37. Wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> now he is faſting and humbling himſelfe in ſack-cloath, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 27. A man would have thought <hi>Ahab</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169752:48"/> will now become a new man, but preſently the byas was turned, by and by he is as bad as ever hee was, he hates Gods Miniſters, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 8. So that ſtill the truth is infallible, that a wicked man, the reaſon why he doth not give over his ſinnes, is not becauſe he cannot, but becauſe hee will not:</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe he will never indeed try whether he can or no, but he is like <hi>Salomons</hi> ſluggard, <hi>vult &amp; non vult,</hi> as the Vulgar tranſlates it, he wils, and he wils not, <hi>Prov. 13. The ſoule of the ſluggard deſireth, and [hath] nothing,</hi> verſ. 4. There is never a wicked man ſhall bee able to ſay to God at the day of judgement, Lord, I would have repented, I did what ever I could to repent, but alas, thou Lord thou knoweſt, I could not: No, <hi>the ſluggard let<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s his field be overgrowne with thorns and nettles, and the wall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169752:48"/> battered downe,</hi> Prov. 24. 31. Happily his field is barren ground and cannot beare fruit; but is that the reaſon that it hath no fruit? Indeed if he did hedge it, and dung it, and plow it, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it, and weed it, and then it would not bring any increaſe, it were another matter, <hi>Cupiunt conſequi non &amp; ſequi,</hi> the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked would arrive in heaven, but he doth not ſtrive to his power for heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a wicked man doth not not repent, becauſe he cannot, but becauſe hee will not, for if he truly and fully would, he could; for the will is the miſtreſſe of all the powers and faculties of ſoule and body: Hee that would bee ſober, might be ſober, unleſſe hee would gagge his mouth, and poure in liquor as into a barrel: He that would ſpeake holyly, may ſpeake holy words, unleſſe hee were dumbe, or one ſhould ſow
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169752:49"/> his lips; Thou wouldeſt leave thy company at the Taverne, thou lyeſt unto God, there is no man hales thee into it as a Calfe to the Shambles with a rope, thou art not tyed there by a chaine, as a Beare by the noſe at the ſtake; No, thou wilt not, <hi>Non velle in cauſa eſt, non poſſe prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenditur,</hi> I will not, is the cauſe, I cannot is pretended: <hi>No, the ſcorner will not goe to the wiſe,</hi> Prov. 15. 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a wicked man doth not, not repent, becauſe hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but becauſe he will not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee ſhewes hee hath ſtill in every action more Can-does, then Wil-does; <hi>Eſau</hi> could weep for repentance when hee ſaw hee had loſt his fathers bleſſing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. but hee runnes a hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ranging at other times, is not this <hi>A will not? Simon Magus</hi> could pray <hi>Peter</hi> to pray for him one while, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169752:49"/> and at other times play the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer, and ſeduce the people, and not looke after his owne, nor <hi>Peters</hi> prayer; is not this <hi>A will not? Saul</hi> could ſacrifice to God, and confeſſe his ſinnes now, but anon he will not obey God, but malice <hi>David:</hi> Is not this, <hi>A will not?</hi> Wicked ſwearers ſay they cannot leave their oaths, and yet in ſuch and ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany they will forbeare; Was not that <hi>A will not?</hi> Wicked drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards ſay that they cannot but be overcome ſometimes, yet they can abſtaine while they are about their worldly profits: Was not this <hi>A will not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, A wicked man doth not, not repent, becauſe he cannot, but becauſe hee will not; for his Can-not, is a willing Can-not; he ſaith, he cannot but ſinne, but might not hee in the loynes of his firſt parents have kept him out of ſinne if he had would? but
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169752:50"/> that is paſt alas! he Cannot now chuſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, There is no man willingly wicked; <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> the very heathen can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, he falſifies with God, and the carnall Philoſophy of man cannot helpe them. Well, to let paſſe the originall Will-not, there is a new actuall Will-not, <hi>E. g.</hi> the Spend-thrift, hee ſaith, hee hath not where withall to give to the poore, he cannot give; but he hath willingly ſpent his money upon potting, or apparrel, or pleaſure, or vanity, and therefore a willing Cannot. Many cannot remember the leſſons of the word preached to repeat them in their houſholds, but their mindes have willingly roved in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, a willing Cannot. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repent, but hee willingly lyes<note place="margin">Quod eſt voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um a parte ante illud eſt voluntarium Axiom.</note> in ſinne, that debarres him from repentance, this alſo is a willing Cannot.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, A wicked man doth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169752:50"/> not not repent, becauſe he cannot, but becauſe he will not; for when the meanes to remove or abate his Cannot are lent him, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly refuſes them. Holy confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence<note place="margin">Qui tollit media voluntarie, voluntarie tollit finem.</note> is a meanes, and he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly refuſes it; powerfull Preaching is a meanes, and hee willingly miſlikes it; to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of his ſinnes is a meanes, and he willingly repines at it. So that the reaſon why a wicked man doth not repent, is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot (though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) but becauſe he will not.</p>
            <p>Now then for anſwer, doe ye aske, Why is a man invited by the Miniſtery to repent, and turne unto the Lord, when he hath not Gods ſecret, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not? becauſe the reaſon why he doth not repent is, becauſe he will not, nor he cannot.</p>
            <p>Yea, but thou wilt ſay, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers cannot bid him, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; He cannot command
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169752:51"/> 
               <hi>Judas,</hi> or <hi>Caine</hi> to beleeve that their ſins may be forgiven them, becauſe Chriſt never dyed for the Reprobate, I anſwer, <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiris Cain,</hi> thou lyeſt <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> Chriſt dyed for thy ſins, and that five wayes:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Proclamation, remiſſion of ſins is to be proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to thee, if thou wilt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; ſo ſaith <hi>Paul, Be it knowne unto you therefore, men and brethren, that through Chriſt is preached unto you forgiveneſſe of ſins,</hi> Act. 13. 38. yea, <hi>among all Nations,</hi> Luke 24. 47. <hi>For to him give all the Prophets witneſſe, that through his Name whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever beleeveth in him ſhall receive forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> Act. 10. 43. ſo that Gods Miniſters are bound to preach that thy ſins may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee, if thou repent and beleeve the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of obligation, thou
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169752:51"/> art bound to beleeve, that thy ſinnes may be forgiven thee in Chriſt, remiſſion of ſins is one of the Articles of thy Creed, that thou art commanded to beleeve, <hi>Repent and beleeve the Goſpel,</hi> Mar. 1. 15. and therefore its called, the Law of faith, <hi>Lex à ligando,</hi> the Law bindeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 2. All are bound to beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt, to the remiſſion of ſins, even re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate and all, they are bound as well as the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; For our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them, to command all treaſures the very ſame things that he commanded them; <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you,</hi> Matth. 28. 20. ſo that thou art bound to beleeve that thy ſinnes may be forgiven thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By way of obſignation; Remiſſion of ſins is ſo farre forth offered unto thee in Chriſt, that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169752:52"/> God hath ſealed this ſerious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in thine owne Conſcience, thine owne Conſcience tels thee, or hath told thee, that it hath in it for to tel thee, that God doth truly offer this grace of Chriſt unto thy ſoule, and thine heart can witneſſe with thee that it is thy fault, if thou doe not repent, and beleeve to the remiſſion of ſins. Thus ſaith our Saviour, <hi>He that beleeveth in him is not condemned, but he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not is condemned already, becauſe he hath not beleeved in the name of the only begotten Sonne of God,</hi> John 3. 18. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome!</hi> The not beleeving it ſelfe accuſeth thee, namely in thine own Conſcience, ſo that thine owne reines check thee for not beleeving that thy ſins can be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given thee.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By way of generall inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for God intended his Sonne
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169752:52"/> generally for Man-kinde, to lay downe a ſufficient price to the remiſsion of ſins for the ſame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the reprobate men, and all comparatively, more then for the reprobate angels generally, I ſay, in reſpect of the condition, that if any man or woman did repent, <hi>they ſhould not periſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly,</hi> Jo. 3. 16. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doe not ſay generally, in reſpect of abſolute purpoſe. Thus ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Verily he tooke not on him the nature of Angels, but he tooke on him the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 16. And leaſt one ſhould thinke, why then he tooke not on him all Man-kinde, therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith it larger, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman,</hi> Gen. 3. 16. in whoſe loynes were all the world. This is no ſmall thing ſaith the ſweet Father, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he did not vouchſafe this mercy to Angels. So then, thou
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169752:53"/> art taxt with a ſinne over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſinne of the Devils in Hel, if thou doſt not repent, and beleeve to the remiſsion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By way of ſpeciall intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too, for all that thou knoweſt, for all that thou knoweſt God meanes to worke Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in thee unto remiſsion of ſins. <hi>Peter</hi> cals upon <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the Sorcerer <hi>Not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, but to repent of this his wickedneſſe and pray God, that if it be poſſible, the thought of his heart might be forgiven him,</hi> Acts 8. 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith the ſame Father; <hi>Peter</hi> did not ſay thus, as if he made any queſtion (or would have him make any queſtioning doubt) of the poſsibility of his forgiveneſſe, if he repented, but only to ſhew the grievous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he was in, that he might provoke him to faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169752:53"/> ſo that thou ſinneſt againſt Gods unſearchable ſecrets and counſel, if thou doſt not beleeve that God may in a ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vouchſafe thee forgiveneſſe of ſins. Excellently then ſaith Saint <hi>Hilary, Omnia omnium,</hi> Chriſt hath ſatisfied enough for all the ſins of all men and women. Whence we may learne, that now its worſe with the wicked man, if he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll live in ſin without amendment of life, then before; if this new Covenant had not been made, accidentally; for now his ſinnes may be forgiven him; God hath offered to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend with him from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the firſt, wherein he could not be forgiven; and to proceed in the new with him, wherein he may, Firſt, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely be forgiven, in regard of Chriſts ſufficiency, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for all ſinne of Man-kinde<note place="margin">Hom. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de paen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> in the world; yea, as <hi>Eccius</hi> ſaith
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169752:54"/> The Redemption of Chriſt his<note place="margin">Diog. <hi>Laer. Proſp. reſp. ob. Vincent</hi>
               </note> bloud is ſufficient, ſo that if there were a 100. <hi>mundi,</hi> a hundred worlds, it might ſerve for all; yea more, were there as many worlds as the Epicureans held, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> infinite worlds. <hi>Aquinas</hi> is bold to ſay, That the bloud of Chriſt is of a ſufficient value to redeeme them all <hi>à toto:</hi> Secondly, mollifiedly, <hi>à tanto,</hi> be forgiven on their owne part, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with Chriſts efficiency. I ſpeake of Chriſts perſwading, exciting, and to ſome generall duties enabling grace, whereby though he doe not give them Free Will, yet he truly proffers them to diminiſh the extreame bondage thereof, and without doubt doth in ſome. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if he be obſtinate in his ſins, he is accidentally I ſay in a more woful condition then ever before, for now, <hi>Curſed is he, becauſe he continues not in all things
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169752:54"/> that are written in the Booke of the Law to doe them;</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves himſelfe upon the old Covenant, and ſhall anſwer for the breach thereof. Now, <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he too, becauſe he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not in the Sonne of God,</hi> he ſhip-wracks himſelfe againſt the New, and ſhall anſwer for the contempt thereof. God comes ſo graciouſly unto him in the power of the diſpenſation of the Goſpel of Chriſt, that it might be the better with him under the Law of faith (although God doe not goe ſo farre with him as with his Elect) but he makes himſelfe guilty of the bloud of the New Teſtament, and turnes this <hi>May be forgiven,</hi> into a double <hi>Never ſhall be forgiven,</hi> yea and by the juſt Judgements of God into a deſperate <hi>Never can be forgiven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe Miniſters may bid them beleeve, becauſe God hath
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169752:55"/> commanded them ſo to preach, yet how can God himſelfe binde <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Dives,</hi> or any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate to beleeve, when Chriſt did not dye for them? or how can God judge them for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in the Sonne of God, who never was incarnate for them? can they be tyed to beleeve that to be ſo, which is not ſo?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. Put that Chriſt did not dye for them, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, or God in the Preacher doth not command them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve an untruth; for faith comes by the word preached, and looke whatſoever the word ſaith, they are bound to beleeve: The word ſaith, <hi>That he dyed for thoſe that beleeve, For thoſe that hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, For thoſe that repent:</hi> The word ſaith, <hi>They are bound to repent,</hi> &amp;c. And if they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, if they do hunger and thirſt after him, then the word aſſures
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169752:55"/> it, <hi>Chriſt dyed for them.</hi> So that, a man cannot be bound to beleeve that which is not ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that were a lye. This is not true, when that which is not, by beleeving is made to bee ſo. <hi>Ergo</hi> It is falſe that a man is an Angel, it is falſe that a man is a Spirit, yet if a man be an Angel, he is a Spirit, that's true. It is falſe that a foole is diſcreet; It is falſe that a foole is wiſe, yet if a foole were diſcreet, he were wiſe, that's true. So it is falſe that a reprobate hungers and thirſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt. It is falſe Chriſt dyed for him in particular, yet if hee doe hunger and thirſt after him, Chriſt did dye for him, is true. It is falſe that a reprobate doth beleeve, and falſe that Chriſt died for the reprobate in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, yet it is true, that if hee doe beleeve, Chriſt dyed for him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That which a man
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169752:56"/> is bound to beleeve, is true: It is true, not only that he is bound to beleeve, but alſo even that thing which hee is bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, but no further then hee is bound to beleeve it. But a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man, <hi>ut ſic,</hi> as yet a wicked man going on in ſin, is no where in Scripture bound to beleeve that Chriſt dyed for him; but hee is bound to beleeve, that is, to bee in <hi>ſtatu quo credat,</hi> in that ſtate wherein he may beleeve, and ſo <hi>mediante hoc ſtatu,</hi> under ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall of that ſtate he is bound to beleeve. Hee that is bound to the antecedent, is bound to the conſequent of that antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt dyed for him in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, is not the faith that every one is immediately bound to, but the ſequel of true faith. <hi>Credere in Chriſtum eſt fides,</hi> to beleeve in Chriſt is the faith it ſelfe, that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169752:56"/> is to goe out of himſelfe, and caſt himſelfe wholly upon Chriſt for his ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God in his ſpeciall mercy gave Chriſt to his elect, to worke their ſalvation, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the condition, for all is from him, our redemption, and the having thereof: Becauſe they could not effect the former Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, he gives them an eaſier, and inables them to doe it. Now God in his general mercy, or in his conditional mercy (ſpeciall too in regard of the Devils, to whom he vouchſafes it not, and in regard of their former ſtricter Covenant, which hee tyes them not to, ſo they doe beleeve) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deviſed a ſufficient meanes for all the worlds ſalvation, ſets the wicked reprobate a rule to live by, namely, faith, repentance, new obedience, which hee will not inable them to doe, nor is hee bound ſo to doe, for a power of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169752:57"/> beleefe was included in their primaeve innocency, as <hi>minus</hi> in <hi>majori. Adam</hi> himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fall, was to goe out of himſelfe, and caſt himſelfe upon another. Now man ſince the Fall, is bound to nothing but the ſame. Here is the difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fall he was to goe out of himſelfe, to deny himſelfe, <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ullius meriti,</hi> and to caſt himſelfe wholly upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Since the Fall, man muſt goe out of himſelfe, and deny himſelfe, <hi>ratione boni</hi> too, and to caſt himſelfe upon a new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; that promiſe was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of bounty, this the promiſe of mercy; that promiſe was in his Sonne God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and this promiſe in his Sonne, both God and man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo that this faith dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the other, but onely in the ſundry modifications of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and object.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the reprobate are juſtly
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169752:57"/> condemned, becauſe they doe not beleeve in <hi>Chriſtum ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſervatorem;</hi> not to ſpeak of <hi>efficacem,</hi> for though they know that Chriſt is a ſufficient Saviour, this is but a <hi>credere Deo,</hi> but a beleeving that God ſayes true, who ſaith that Chriſt is ſufficient; they may beleeve that Chriſt is a ſufficient Saviour, but ſure it is, that they doe not beleeve in Chriſt a ſufficient Saviour.</p>
            <closer>The Lord ſtabliſh the peace of Sion, in heart and minde, through Jeſus Chriſt our Saviour.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:58"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHich Title thou ſhalt well deſerve, if with thy Pen thou mendeſt, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt with a candid cenſure thoſe ſmall faults, if any there bee, which have ſcaped uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected from the Preſſe. I ſhall offer thee as a motive hereunto, That it is an old Copy of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Author, whoſe helpe wee could not have, which is uſuall in Printing.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169752:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
